A Guide to the J. Rives Childs Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
J. Rives Childs Papers 1869-1983
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9256-m, -n
This collection consists of ca. 4,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift to the Library from the Honorable James Rives Childs through Mrs. Hilda Noel Schroetter of Richmond, Virginia on 8 Sep 1982, and 20 Jan 1983.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Rives Childs was a retired foreign service officer.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of correspondence; manuscripts, particularly his memoirs Brave Music of a Distant Drum; photographs; and printed materials such as itineraries, newsletters, clippings, articles and Randolph-Macon college publicity. These papers relate to his activities during the 1960s and 1970s, especially his interest in Randolph-Macon, Casanova, the Middle East, and the writing and attempted publication of his memoirs. There is a small group of letters written to his mother, Lucy Howard (Brown) Rives, (a Lynchburg, Virginia schoolteacher) from the 1870s through the 1890s. Correspondents inlcude Edward Christian Glass, Peter A. Iseman, Marco Leeflang, Robert Murphy, and Luther White. There are brief notes from Jacob Javits and Hugh Scott and a copy of a letter to Warren Beatty regarding Childs' memories of John Reed and Louise Bryant.
Arrangement
These papers are arranged chronologically into three series: correspondence; manuscripts; printed material, photographs and miscellaneous. Folders are arranged alphabetically in manuscripts and printed material, photographs and miscellaneous.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence 1869-1983 (Box 1)
    7 folders
  - Correspondence 1981-1983, n.d. (Box 2)
    3 folders
- Manuscripts
  - "Book Collecting" post-1973, TMs and electrostatic copies (Box 2)
  - "Boxed-In" ca. 1974, TMs, copy and TMs w/corrections (Box 2)
  - "Brave Music of a Distant Drummer" ca. 1978, TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 2)
    Contents and Chapters 1-3
  - "Brave Music of a Distant Drummer" ca. 1978, TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 2)
    Chapters 4-7
  - "Brave Music of a Distant Drummer" ca. 1978, TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 3)
    Chapters 8-23 (5 folders)
  - "Brave Music of a Distant Drummer" ca. 1978, TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 4)
    Chapters 24-29 and Section I-III (6 folders)
  - "Brave Music of a Distant Drummer" ca. 1978, TMs (electrostatic copy) (Box 5)
    Sections IV-VIII (2 folders)
  - Material Related to Casanova1956-1979, n.d. (Box 5)
  - "Encounters--Mixed and Missed" post-1960, TMs and electrostatic copy (Box 5)
  - [Untitled] "...l'etude des institutions et connaitre les costumes du pays et la vie de la societe americaine." by S. Iordanow ca. 1960, TMs (carbon copy) (Box 5)
  - "Foreign Relations" ca. 1950, TMs and electrostatic copy (Box 5)
  - Material Related to "Henry Miller" 1947, 1960, n.d., TMs and electrostatic copy (Box 5)
  - "A Psychic Episode" 1965, 1974-1975, TMs and electrostatic copy (Box 5)
  - "Soviet Russia Fifty-four Years Afterwards" post-1975, TMss and printed copy (Box 5)
  - "The Survivors" 1965, TMss & printed copy (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Titles 1935-1975, TMss (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Pages n.d., TMss and electrostatic copy (Box 6)
- Printed Material, Photographs and Miscellaneous
  - Brochures 1972-1982, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Bulletins and Reports re Randolph Macon College 1966-1982, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Clippings: Magazines 1933, 1937, 1962-1982, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Clippings: Newspapers 1930, 1945-1982, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Itineraries 1961-1982 (Box 6)
  - Lists (Chiefly membership directories) 1973-1982, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Memorabilia 1981-1982, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous: Re Miss Lucy H. Brown (Childs) 1873-1890 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1957-1982, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Newsletters 1974-1982 (Box 7)
  - Notes: Various Lectures and Miscellany 1976, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Memoirs and Letters of Charlotte Elizabeth Young, 1895-1982 ca. 1982 (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets re Randolph Macon College 1974-1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - The Rewards of Book Collecting 1962 (Box 7)
  - Pamphlets--Miscellaneous; Various authors, including JRC 1908-1976 (Box 8)
  - Pamphlets, Miscellaneous 1966-1983, n.d. (Box 8)
    4 folders
  - Photographs & Prints: J. Rives Childs and Relatives 1880-1938, 1973-1979, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Photographs & Persons 1931, 1974-1978, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Photographs & Prints: Places 1978, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Print: James Rives Childs and Etched Copper Plate ca. 1921 (Box 9)
  - U.S. Diplomatic Passport (Cancelled) 1963 (Box 9)
  - Poster 32"x40" "The NSA International Affairs Institute" Presents Ambassador James Rives Childs--"Bitter Roots: The Basis of the Present Conflicts in the Middle East" 1977